<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon concerning the Eucharist Deliuered on Easter day in Oxford.</title>
            <author>James, Richard, 1592-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14200</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843368</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177000</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240948153</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14441</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107672</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843368e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 741:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon concerning the Eucharist Deliuered on Easter day in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>James, Richard, 1592-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 [i.e. 18] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Harper?] for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at his shop at the black Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard James.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>P. 18 misnumbered 14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Lord's Supper --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177000:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177000:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON CONCERNING <hi>THE</hi> Eucharist.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED ON <hi>EASTER</hi> DAY IN OXFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>IACOBVS SANNASARIVS.</bibl>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Mentem animumque Deo non thura aut exta parate.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the blacke Beare in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1629.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177000:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177000:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE <hi>EVCHARIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MAT. cap. 26. ver. 26, 27, 28.</bibl>
                  <p>And as they were eating, Iesus tooke bread, and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it, and brake it, and gaue it to the Disciples; and said, Take, eate, this is my body.</p>
                  <p>And he tooke the cup, and gaue thankes, and gaue it to them, saying, Drinke ye all of it:</p>
                  <p>For this is my bloud of the new Testament, which is shed for many for the remission of sinnes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue already heard enough for your beliefe, and the solemne mysteriousnesse of this day, from the Gospell read vnto you. To speake more, were to derogate from the reuerence of the one, and the authority of the other: neither is it possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177000:3"/>for me in this part, to speake any thing equall or second vnto the nature of a subiect so transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which poses the conceit and language both of men and Angels. A God borne man at Christe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, crucified on good Friday, &amp; early this day in the morning againe raised from death in our flesh, to farre more glory and maiesty, then if we should on a sudden see the Sunne in fullheate and lustre strooke out of darknesse, and like a Bridegroome reioycing to runne his course. I can onely say in astonishment, O the height, O the depth, O the vnsearchablenesse of Gods wayes, iudgements, and knowledge! Thus I must say when I begin; and when I haue done, I haue againe nothing to conclude, but wonder.</p>
            <p>In the meane while therefore, since I must break silence, I haue made choice of a lower Treatise, neither vnsutable to the time, and agreeing to the present occasion, concerning the presence or Christ in the Sacrament: <hi>This is,</hi> saith hee, <hi>my body; This is my bloud of the new Testament.</hi> These, and the like Sacramentall words, when they fell first from the lips of our Sauiour, seem'd strange: but they haue since that time in the mutinous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting spirits of later age, growne vp with more terrible effects; in so much as the history of the Sacrament is a history of bloud, fitter to efferate mens minds vnto a battell, then to inuite them by the rehearsall vnto a sacrifice of peace and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing. The Chapters are diuided with so many Schismes, and pend with swords and firebrands-slaughters,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177000:3"/>warres and rumours of warre are the Antichristian newes. So that when we cast backe our consideration hereon, wee cannot be without horrour; to see the curse of them in the Prophet fallen vpon the most wofull estate of Christendome. Let their table be a snare before them, and their prosperity their ruine. Concerning this body and this bloud of our Eucharist, myriads of mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies haue bin torne and broken, and vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded almost into no elements; and of mens bloud hath bin shed enough to colour the Ocean: Boundlesse herein I might be, if I had pleasure in remembrance of ruine; but for this present I shall deliuer vnto you something else: and especially, the meaning of Christs Sacramentall words from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his Apostles, who likely should be their owne best Commentaries. What saith Christ vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, and vnto his Disciples in the sixt Chapter of the Euangelist Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> tis the most proper Gospell for the Sacrament, and therefore I will read it in part vnto you, beginning at the 24 Verse. <hi>Now when the people saw that Iesus was not there, neither his Disciples, they also tooke shipping, and came to</hi> Capernaum <hi>seeking to Iesus. And when they had found him on the other side of the Sea, they said vnto him, Rabbi, when camest thou hither? Iesus answered them and said: Verily, verily, I say vnto you; yee seeke me not because ye saw the miracles, but because yee ate of the loues, and were filled. Labour not for the meat which perisheth, but for the meat that endureth vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting life, which the Sonne of man shall giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177000:4"/>you: For him hath God the Father sealed. This is to you the worke of God, that yee beleeue on him whom hee hath sent. I am the bread of life, hee that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me shall not hunger, and he that beleeueth in me shall neuer thirst. I am the liuing bread, I am the bread that came downe from heauent: the bread that I will giue is my flesh, which I will giue for the life of the world. Then the Iewes stroue among themselues saying; How can this man giue vs his flesh to eat? Then Iesus said vnto them, Verily, verily I say vnto yau; Except ye eat the flesh of the Sonne of man and drinke his blood, yee haue no life in you; Whosoeuer eateth my flesh and drinketh my blond, hath eternall life, and I will raise him vp at the last day. For my flesh is meat indeed, and my blood is drinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Hee that eateth my flesh and drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in mee, and I in him. As the liuing Father hath sent me, so liue I by the Father; and hee that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me. euen he shall liue by me. This is the bread which came downe from heauen: not as your Fathers haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Manna, and are dead. Hee that eateth this bread shall liue for euer. These things spake hee in the Synagogue as he taught in</hi> Capernaum: <hi>Many therefore of his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, when they heard this, said; This is an hard say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who can heare it? But Iesus knowing in himselfe, that his Disciples murmured at this, said vnto them, Doth this offend you? What then if yee should see the Sonne of man ascend vp where he was before? It is the spirit that quickneth, the flesh profiteth nothing. The words that I speake vnto you are spirit and life.</hi> Parallell vnto this place are many others, which I will also repear, because they agree to make vp the same Catholique
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177000:4"/>sence and doctrine. Thus we read in Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the 22. Chap. at the 19, 20. and 17. Verses: <hi>He tooke the Cup and gaue thankes, and said; Take this and drinke it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. And he took bread, &amp; when he had giuen thanks, he brake it, and gaue to them saying; This is my body which is giuen for you, doe this in remembrance of mee.</hi> Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the first to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the 11. Chapter, beginning at the 23. Verse. <hi>For I haue receiued of the Lord, that which I haue also deliuered vnto you;</hi> to wit, <hi>that the Lord Iesus in the night that hee was betrayed, tooke bread: and when he had giuen thankes hee brake it, and said; Take, eat, this is my Body which is broken for you; This doe in remembrance of me; For as often as ye shall eat this bread, and drinke this cup, yee shew the Lords death till hee come.</hi> And according to this institution and paraphrase, wee haue also the phrase of the same Apostle in the 3. to the <hi>Romans. To be iustified by the blood, that is, by Faith in the blood, and Passion of Christs righteousnesse, saith he, by the Faith of Iesus Christ, vnto all, and vpon all that beleeue, and are iustified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Iesus, whom God hath set forth to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation through faith in his blood, to declare his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse by the forgiuenesse of sinnes, that are passed, through the patience of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so this Apostolicall and Euaagelicall foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being laid with firme and choice stones, from the most sufficient quarry of the new Testament; a shame it were to build vpon it a doctrine of stubble and vncertaine superstition.</p>
            <p>But without Prouerbe and Allegory, now briefly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177000:5"/>to resolue the doubt, that we neither murmure or striue amongst our selues, as did the Iewes, or fall backe from Christ with too much astonishment, as did they, and at that first time many of his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The bread and wine in which we Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, is in Spirit and Truth; and forth-shewing, and remembrance, and by faith in his Passion, to vs the body and blood of Christ: if we beleeue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member assuredly that 1624 yeares since Christ was borne for our redemption, crucified for our sinnes, and rose againe for our glory: This is the doctrine taught by Christ, by his Apostles, and peraduenture by all the greatest Doctors of the Church in the first thousand yeeres after them. I am not willingly ouerbold of any assurance and thtrefore I say perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, though a hard taske it would be for an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary man to conuince vs if we omitted the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of that aduerbe, excepting some Diuines, who in all ages are like those some Orators of whom <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Iudaeus</hi> speakes in this manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. They blow vp their vulgar readers and auditors into strange imaginations; they leauen their Treatise with phantafies, and obscure the truth in a heape and aumber of toyles and muthologies. Take away these excesses of Eloquence and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torike; and againe, take away some few Spiders who from the leafe and blossome of Scripture chose to gather poyson where the Bee suckes hony: According to that of <hi>Tertullian: Nec periclitor dicere ipsas quoque Scripturas, sic esse ex Dei voluntate disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177000:5"/>vt hoereticis materias subministreut cùm legam opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere hoereses esse, quae sine Scripturis esse nonpossent.</hi> And then the sincere primitiue antiquity of the Church shall deliuer the same simple truth, which I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related from the fountaine of the Gospell. Let Saint <hi>Austen</hi> for breuity be heard in the name of the rest. <hi>Si flagitium aut facinus videtur iubere Scriptura ne dubites figuratam locutionem.</hi> If the Scripture (saith he) seeme to command any crime or wickednesse, doubt not but the speech is figuratiue. It saith, <hi>Except you eat the flesh of the Sonne of man and drinke his blood, ye haue no life in you.</hi> Here is horridneffe and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in shew commanded; therefore it is a figuratiue speech willing vs to communicate in the passion of our Sauiour, and remember with desire and profit, that his flesh was for our sake crucified and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Crosse. Againe, <hi>Non dubitauit Dominus.</hi> Our Lord said this is my body, when he deliuered the signe of it; and this third place of his is most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. <hi>Huius sacrificij caro &amp; sanguis ante aduêntum Christi per victimas similitudinum promittebatur, in pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione Christi per ipsam veritatem reddebatur, post ascèn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum Christi per Sacramentum memoriae celebratur.</hi> The flesh and the blood of this Sacrifice (saith he) before the comming of Christ was shadowed in offerings of type and similitude; in the passion of Christ himselfe was giuen in very truth of our flesh and blood: after the Ascension of Christ we yet still ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the same sacrifice in a Sacrament of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Should we from the times of Saint <hi>Ansten</hi> fall downe vnto <hi>Alfred</hi> the famous founder of our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177000:6"/>Vniuersity. Here we shall find a Sainted and most learned man, <hi>Iohannes Scotus Erigena,</hi> writing two books in confirmation of the self same Diuinity: and in the reigne of King <hi>Aethelrede,</hi> we yet read Abbot <hi>Alfric,</hi> though a man papall enough, still instructing his Saxon cure, that Christ is no otherwise corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this bread of the Sacrament in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then he was in the old, Manna, a Lambe, a Lyon, or a Rocke: yea, and their later <hi>Scotus</hi> also, sauing the authority of the Roman Church in Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirds new Lateranc reed, Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth our doctrine to be <hi>intellectum facilem &amp; verio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem secundum apparentiam;</hi> the more apparantly true and easie sense of Scripture. Besides if we goe vnto their traditionall arguments of sleshy liue appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Sacrament, <hi>Alexander de Ales,</hi> as a thing notorious to the whole world, cannot refuse to say that many of them were done, <hi>humana procuratione &amp; sorte Diabolica,</hi> by knaues imposture and diuelish magique. From all which we may boldly say in the confidence of an old English treatise to this same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. <hi>Here ye may see that this new determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the sacred Dost is nought, for it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerseth and grieueth the faith and the tradition of the greatest and the best men that euer were: and also it is peruerting of the customable beliefe continued generally in Christs Church into the vnbinding of Sathanas, and that continueth ghit in faithfull men, and shall into doomysday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Romanists had eares to heare either God or good men, they would shame to play the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177000:6"/>Manachies with Christs bodie, and contract him to the creatures of bread and wine, to enchaunt him to a residence in euery abiect, sordid, and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Friets Oaste; to make him solid in wine, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid in bread, to be together flesh and blood both in the one and the other. But tis not impossible for their fancy to conceiue this and much more, who could spy out the traitor <hi>Garnets</hi> head and face in a straw. And for their impiety, their couetous and ambitious atheisme, they dare more Tis but Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimy to transubstantiate Christ: they also diuide him for lazie respect, as tis most probable, seuering the blood from the body in the halfe Communion of lay men; with pretence lest their long beards should peraduenture draw vp some drop of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: they hauing long since shaued away all the honour and reuerence of a man from their owne cheekes, in hatred and despight of their fellow Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in the Greeke Church, refusing to stoope vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tyranny of the Westerne Babylon. Tra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiat bread and wine into Christs body? with what reason? nay by what miracle? Entities say the Philosophers are not to be multiplied without cause, much lesse miracles. We see bread &amp; wine in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament after the cōsecration, we smell it, we tast it, we handle it, we digest it, and yet is it nothing else but Christ? the very same body in which he suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the very same substance in which he sits at the right hand of God the Father in glory? Where be his lin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aments, where appeares his Maiesty and br<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtnesse? His face in the transfiguration did
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177000:7"/>shine as the Sunne on Mount Thabor, when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared talking with <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> vnto the three Disciples. Or if from the Tragedy of the Crosse the Eucharist receiue him, why should not the same miracle make his side again send forth an issue of water and bloud, to wash away the murthers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cests, rapines and blasphemies, which for many hundred yeeres all secular principalities did with griefe, behold and for feare dared not reuenge on the neckes of the Papall Clergy. Must we of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity deny our senses, by whom we enforme our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or shall we be irreligious? How then shall we beleeue the Apostle from an argument of sense, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ioyfull resurrection of our mortall bodies? We see the corne dye and rot, and then spring vp againe into a blade, and stalke, and eare, laden with encrease; and thence wee would gladly say with S. <hi>Paul:</hi> So shall our dead bodies be raised vp, and spread themselues into all varieties of liuelihood: into armes, and legs, and veines, and sinewes and arteries, and then this mortall shall flourish im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortally, as well in blisse as being. But the Monkes, and Popes, and Cardinals haue stollen away or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquated, by a new awe of superstition, all the trust of sense and reason. Should men haue continued in their senses, and their reason, perfit of their creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as God made them, they would neuer haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Religion to be made so costly vnto their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, for the kissing of old bones, shirts, smockes, muckingers, pantables and petticotes, or other such like raffe and trumpery, with the gaines of which,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177000:7"/>the Roman Antichrist hath now long since built vp, and drest the superarrogant vice of his triple Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. I may say vnto them as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith vnto the Stoicks: <hi>His praestigijs regna nata vobis sunt, &amp; impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, &amp; diuitiae, &amp; tantae quidem, vt omnia quae vbique sint, vestra esse dicatis;</hi> With these new fangled tyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sill Diuinities you haue established vnto your selues kingdomes and Empires, and with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell you cry out, that riches and all is yours. We see with open eyes within distance, and yet we must confesse that we are deceiued; we taste bread in the Sacrament, and poore lay people, if they will giue vs the cup also, though neuer so much dasht with water, with such food in quantity we can liue, and blesse God both for a temporall and spirituall suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; yet when we thus eat, we must say that we eat nothing. For so saies their Byshop <hi>Gwymundus</hi> Scholler vnto <hi>Lanfrancke</hi> Archbyshop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who after his false Masters example, wrought anciently against the learned, religious, and noble <hi>Berengarius</hi> defending our truth. If to make experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wee doe liue vpon the consecrate bread and both digest and bedraught it, as nature vses: if by chance we see it nibled with mice, putrified with wormes, or deuoured by dogs, he will haue vs say and beleeue that all this is onely an illusion of sense, such as <hi>Mary Maudlins</hi> was, when she tooke Christ for the Gardener, and that the sacred bread, free from all corruption, is by the seruice of Angels, or selfe power, taken vp into heauen. Lord! in the negligence of doting and prophane Priests, how
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177000:8"/>many Sacraments then, how many thousands and millions are treasured vp to Diuinity? Christ in this multiplication would himselfe fill vp the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of his heauenly Mansions. After this first great vnbeliefe and deniall of our selues, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gainefull impostures haue not beene thrust vpon Christian soules? Transubstantiating also the linnen corporall of the acrament into the very body and blood of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease their staple of reliques. The supremacie of Rome ouer all Princes and Nations, besides the Turke and Tartar, who will one day bring home to her dores the iust vengeance of that strumpets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. So many limboes, purgatories, Peter-pencd annats, indulgencies, merits of pilgrimage, vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall impossible vowes, and the infallibility of the Popes Chayre: God, if it be his blessed will, raise vp some magnanimous Prince to rescue Christian people from such a senslesse stupidity as hath for a long time astonisht them: either Prince or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet for so great a worke of reformation and restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Christian peoples fiue sound senses can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be effected without a mīghty power of sword or miracle. But here peraduenture some men will wish vs to take heed, lest we vie the assurance of our senses against the authority of Scripture. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelists say, <hi>This is my body, This is my bloud:</hi> and must not we of force say the like? Is the bread con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate, is Christs body and the wine, is his bloud not consubstantiate nor transubstantiate, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally, figuratiuely, and effectually to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177000:8"/>as haue a faithfull remembrance of Christs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, vnto which wee are confirmed by the sensible experience of the Apostles. <hi>And the Word was made flesh</hi> (saith Saint <hi>Iohn) and dwelt amongst vs, and we saw the glory thereof as the glory of the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne of the Father, full of grace and truth.</hi> And againe, in his Epistle. <hi>That which was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which we haue heard, which we haue seene with our eye<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which we haue looked vpon, and our hands haue hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the word of life. For the life appeared, and we haue seene it, and beare witnesse, and shew vnto you the eternall life which was with the Father, and appeared vnto vs.] That I say, which we haue seene and heard, declare we vnto you, that ye may also haue fellowship with vs, and that our fellowship also may be with the Father, and with his Sonne Iesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sacrament was ordained for other purpose then to pose our senses. To callvs still into a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our reconciliation vnto God the Father by the birth, merits, and passion of the Sonne. To call vs to a reconciliation of our selues, one vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. <hi>As God forgaue vs, so should wee heere mutually exchange forgiuenesse.</hi> Certainly this briefe aduice and intention of a Sacrament is farre more holy, then the preparation of him in <hi>Wiclifs</hi> time, who for the practice of the Sacramenr against the ensuing so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of Easter, did fit at the request of some friends seuenty two questions and answers, aecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the number of Christs Disciples or the worlds languages. The questions, some of them are these. If an Angell or the soule of a dead
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177000:9"/>priest in another mans body assumed, or a Priest blessed already in heauen may confect Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. If a Priest may consecrate one part of the Oast and leaue the other vnconsecrate. If it be better to consecrate with huge, lusty, strong wine, then with small and feeble. Whither all the parts of Christ glorified bee in the Sacrament. Whither all that is consecrated in the bread be also in the wine. Whither more then foure words be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the consecration of the body, and more then fiue for the bloud. What a Priest must doe, if after the consecration hee finde no wine in the Chalice. What a Priest ought to doe, if after the consecration, he see flesh or a little young boy in the Sacrament. What man not giuen ouer to a reprobate sense will not easily vnderstand the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of these men, stuffing their missals and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall bookes with so many impertinent vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, so many foolish and darke imaginations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing as the Gentiles did before them, to see cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the invisible power of God in the visibility of his creation, changing the truth of God into a lye, and worshipping and seruing the creature more then the Creator, who is blessed for euer: with these propositions I desire not to moue laughter, but both in my selfe and you a sad disdaine of the most foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Cimmerian darkenesse, which the Roman ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny had drawne ouer our senses, our reason, our iudgement, and all the intellectuall faculties of the soule, which in the dayes of our Ancestors was at the reuolution of this feast to combate with so
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177000:9"/>many meteors of Diuinity. The irreligion, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the presumption of the Roman Church in this part is infinite. Christ said at the Passeouer that <hi>he would no more drinke of the fruit of the Vine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the kingdome of God be come;</hi> And they at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures in their kingdome haue hurld him into the cup. He said he would no more eat the bread, and they make him deuoure it. <hi>He tooke bread, and hee tooke wine, and said, this bread and this cup is my new Testament.</hi> And they say no, here is neither this nor that, but in visible sensible bread nothing is, but Christ inuisible. Wee see not that which is, and what wee see, that is nothing Yes, in this nothing with them, Christ is fully as long &amp; broad, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent as at the day of his passion, receiued in whole, and euery part and crumme entirely into the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rownesse of our mouthes. They read riddles, and not Sacraments. <hi>Christ tooke bread, and brake it when he had giuen thankes, and gaue it to his Disciples,</hi> and they take bread, and by consecration make a Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis of substance, and then aduise in their leud treatises how they may breake the white round ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident of their Sacramentall wafer without pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and tearing asunder a legge or arme of Christ. These and the like blasphemies when to establish against our Wicklesse, the Friers and Bishops had gathered themselues together at Poules in London, heare of that reuerend man what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For I dare truly say,</hi> saith he, <hi>that if these
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177000:10"/>things were sothe, Christ and his Seints dyed hecetycks and tho more parte of holy Kirke vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued now heresie. And therefore deuout men supposen that this counsell of Freris at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don was with erthdyn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</note>
               <hi>for they put an heresie vpon Christ and Sentis in heu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, where-fore the earth trembled, and Faylande mans voice) answeared for God, as it did in t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, when hee was dambned to bodily death.</hi> The earth euer shakes when any violence is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his body. After he had once yeelded vp the Ghost of our mortality, his body resurrectiue both of himselfe and vs, by that signe leades capriuity captiue. He cried with a loud voyce, and yeelded vp the ghost, and behold the vaile of the Temple was rent in twaine, and the earth did quake, and the stones were clouen, and the graues did open themselues, and many bodies of the Saints which slept arose, and came out of the graues after his resurrection. <hi>Ioseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> an honourable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour, desires in loue to conserue his body in a new tombe, which hee had hewed out in a rocke, and for that purpose rolled a great stone to the doore of the Sepulchre. The Priests and Pharises assembled to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and to make all more sure, seale the stone, and gard it with a watch, but in the dawning of this day there was againe a great earth-quake; The Angell descended from heauen, and rolled backe the stone from the doore, and sat vpon it, and for feare of him, the keepers were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177000:10"/>astonied, and became as dead men. Aske our Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and also a third time when the Friers at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don will imprison his body in bread, or drowne it in the Chalice, the earth shakes anew. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather heare the voyce of the Angell vnto the women; <hi>Surrexit, non est hic.</hi> Iesus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> which on good Friday was crucified on the crosse at <hi>Ierusalem</hi> by the <hi>Iewes;</hi> which is, so much as in them lies, still crucified by the degenerous <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in their prostitute Sacrament: hee is risen, hee is not here, hee is entred into heauen, hee is made higher then the heauens, hee sits at the right hand of Maiestie in the glory and blisse of heauen. Gaze wee must not any more after a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Christs body, vntill in a second fulnesse of time it shall please him againe to descend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the ruines of this world into an eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation. Euen at that time the powers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen shall be shaken, and wee shall see the Sonne of man come in a cloud with power and great glorie. For the Lord himselfe, saith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> shall descend from heauen with a shout, and with the voyce of the Archangell, and with the trumpet of GOD; and the dead in Christ shall rise first. Then shall wee which liue and remaine be caught vp with them also in the clouds, to meete the LORD in the aire; and so shall wee euer be with the LORD. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comfort your selues one another with these
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177000:11"/>words. And againe, vntill the consummation of that day, reioyce in the mysterie of this, from the words of the same Apostle: GOD <hi>is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested in the flesh, iustified in the Spirit, seene of Angels, beleeued on in the world, and receiued vp in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177000:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>